foreign
[Music]
suppose we have a triangle with sides of
length a b and c and suppose that the
angle opposite of C is called Theta the
law of cosines provides a relationship
between these four values to derive the
law of cosines we drop a perpendicular
from the top of the triangle to the base
and that creates two sub right triangles
the hypotenuse of the yellow triangle is
B which means that the height of that
yellow triangle is B times the sine of
theta while the base of that triangle is
B times the cosine of theta this means
that the base of the blue right triangle
is a minus B times the cosine of theta
but now that we have a right triangle
pictured we can draw squares off the
legs of the right triangle and a square
off the hypotenuse of the right triangle
like this these squares have area B
times the sine of theta squared
quantity a minus B cosine Theta squared
and c squared by the Pythagorean theorem
we know that c squared equals the
quantity a minus B times cosine Theta
squared plus the quantity B times sine
of theta squared but now we can apply
algebraic rules along with the
Pythagorean trigonometric identity to
see that c squared equals a squared plus
b squared minus 2 times a times B times
cosine Theta this is the law of cosines
and this means that we've used the
Pythagorean theorem to prove the law of
cosines we can also plug theta equals pi
over 2 into the law of cosines to prove
the Pythagorean theorem and that means
that the two theorems are equivalent
you may be wondering if the diagram
works when the angle Theta is obtuse
instead here is such a triangular
diagram with sides of length a b and c
and an obtuse angle Theta across from C
in this instance we can drop an altitude
and then draw a horizontal line to build
this right triangle inside this blue
right triangle we see a yellow right
triangle with an angle Pi minus Theta so
its height is B times the sine of Pi
minus Theta while its base is B times
the cosine of pi minus Theta however we
know that b times the sine of Pi minus
Theta is actually equal to B times the
sine of theta and B times the cosine of
pi minus Theta is negative B times the
cosine of theta this means that the
pictured blue right triangle has a
height of B times sine of theta and a
base of length a minus B times a cosine
of theta so we can apply the Pythagorean
theorem again to get this exact same
identity that c squared equals the
quantity a minus B cosine Theta squared
plus b times sine Theta squared once
again algebraic manipulation will
provide the law of cosines in this case